Finding Aid for the John Egerton Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
John Egerton Papers
1950’s–2003
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0128
38.63 linear_feet
Scope and Content Note
The John Egerton Papers, 1950s-2003, include correspondence, manuscripts of writings, speeches, research materials, publication materials, publicity for books, reviews, legal and financial documents, memorabilia, clippings and photographs, programs from cultural events, scrapbooks and periodicals on race relations and school desegregation, and audio and video tapes. The ninety-one boxes of this collection cover approximately 38 linear feet. Major topics include civil rights, desegregation, race relations, Southern history, and Southern food. The collection is arranged in chronological order, beginning with Egerton’s early writings in the army and in public relations while in graduate school at the University of Kentucky and continuing through his extensive work as a free-lance writer and author of many books. These papers offer a fascinating insight into the career of a non-fiction writer in the late twentieth and early twenty-first centuries.
Approximately thirty-two boxes of the collection contain materials relating to Egerton’s work as a writer for periodicals and as a participant in many conferences and projects concerned with civil rights and desegregation. These materials include the manuscripts and the extensive research for his articles on subjects such as civil rights, labor relations, education reform and equality of opportunity, Southern history, and Southern food. Especially important are the manuscripts and materials for the major articles he wrote for American Heritage and The New York Times Magazine. These boxes also contain correspondence related to the articles, highlights being letters from James Earl Ray, John Popham, Claude Pepper, Alex Haley, and Will Campbell.
The most extensive part of the collection is the material for Egerton’s books. Included are the manuscripts, research materials, correspondence, photographs, and publicity materials for A Mind to Stay Here, The Americanization of Dixie, Visions of Utopia, Nashville: The Faces of Two Centuries, Side Orders, Unfinished Business, and Shades of Gray. There is also a copy of the manuscript for Nashville: An American Self-Portrait, but the materials related to this book are deposited with the Metro Nashville Archives.
Perhaps the most significant part of the collection is the material related to his books Generations, Southern Food, and Speak Now Against the Day. The nine boxes containing Generations are comprised of manuscripts, including the Japanese edition, and extensive research materials. There are taped interviews as well as the transcripts of the tapes, much publicity material, many photographs, most taken by Egerton,and voluminous correspondence, especially with the Ledford family. The materials for Southern Food is in six boxes and contains multiple copies of the manuscript, reserach materials, correspondence, photographs, and publicity materials. The seventeen boxes of materials for Speak Now Against the Day include the tapes and tape transcripts constituting part of the research for the book and contributed to the University of North Carolina’s Southern Oral History Project. Additional tapes contain interviews with Robert Penn Warren, Gene Graham, and Studs Terkel. There are copies of the manuscript and eight boxes of extensive research materials and correspondence, including letters from Wilma Dykeman, John Popham, C. Vann Woodward, Alexander Heard, and John Hope Franklin. Two boxes contain photographs, photostats, and photocopies of footage from March of Time newsreels.
Subject Files contain many issues of Integrated Education: Race and Schools, Report of the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights, and Inequality in Education. There are also scrapbooks of newspaper clippings pertaining to education issues in 1950-1951, especially in California.
Biographical Sketch
John Edgerton was born in Atlanta, Georgia, June 14, 1935, the son of William G. Egerton, a traveling salesman, and his wife, Rebecca White Egerton. The family soon settled in Cadiz, Kentucky, where John Egerton remained until leaving to attend Western Kentucky University, 1953-1954. From 1954 until 1956, he served in the United States Army. He earned a B.A. at the University of Kentucky in 1958 and an M.A. in 1960. In 1957 he married Ann Elizabeth Bleidt, and the couple have two sons.
Between 1958 and 1960, Egerton was with the Public Relations Department of the University of Kentucky, and from 1960 to 1965, he was the Director of Public Information for the University of South Florida. He was a staff writer for Southern Education Report, 1965-1969, and for Race Relations Reporter, 1969-1971.
In 1971, Egerton began his career as a free-lance reporter. He was a contributing editor for Saturday Review of Education (1972-1973), Race Relations Reporter (1973-1974), and Southern Voices (1974-1975). From 1973-1975, he was a writer for Atlanta’s Southern Regional Council. In 1977-1978, he was journalist-in-residence at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Egerton has written or edited eleven non-fiction books and contributed over two hundred articles to periodicals. He has also been a participant in and writer for many projects or conferences dealing with desegregation and civil rights.
- Suivez Moi (14th Armored Cavalry Yearbook, 1955) (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous materials relating to Egerton’s student career, University of Kentucky, 1957-58 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- University of Kentucky Public Relations materials by Egerton, 1958-60 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- University of South Florida Public Relations materials by Egerton, 1960-65 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- The Controversity-Manuscript (1965) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- The Controversity-Correspondence-Outgoing (Box 1, Folder 6)
- The Controversity-Correspondence-Incoming (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Rhodesia (The Atlantic Report, Atlantic Monthly, Sept. 1965)-Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Rhodesia-Research and Background Materials-Handwritten Notes (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Rhodesia-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Rhodesia-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Rhodesia-Research and Background Materials-Newspaper clippings (Box 1, Folder 12)
- The New Missionary (The Christian Century, Dec. 8, 1965)-Typescript of Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 13)
- New University in the Congo (The Christian Century, Jan. 12, 1966)-Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 14)
- TVA: The Halo Slips-Manuscript (1967) (Box 2, Folder 1)
- TVA: The Halo Slips-Galley Proofs (Box 2, Folder 2)
- TVA: The Halo Slips-Early Drafts (Box 2, Folder 3)
- TVA: The Halo Slips-Research and Background Materials-Interviews/Handwritten Notes (Box 2, Folder 4)
- TVA: The Halo Slips-Research and Background Materials-Articles 1957-65 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- TVA: The Halo Slips-Research and Background Materials-Articles 1966-67 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- TVA: The Halo Slips-Documents Pertaining to Court Case (Box 2, Folder 7)
- TVA: The Halo Slips-Documents Pertaining to Court Case (Box 2, Folder 8)
- TVA: The Halo Slips-Documents Pertaining to Court Case (Box 2, Folder 9)
- TVA: The Halo Slips-Correspondence Pertaining to Court Case (Box 2, Folder 10)
- TVA: The Halo Slips-Correspondence-Outgoing (1965-67) (Box 2, Folder 11)
- TVA: The Halo Slips-Correspondence-Incoming (1966-67) (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Mike Horowitz Article (1967)-Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Horowitz-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Horowitz-Correspondence-Outgoing (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Horowitz-Correspondence-Incoming (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Higher Education for “High Risk” Students (1968)-Manuscript (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Academic Games Article-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Games-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Games-Correspondence-Incoming (Box 3, Folder 4)
- State Universities and Black Americans (Southern Education Foundation, 1969)- Manuscript (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Cubans in Miami (1969)-Manuscript (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Cubans in Miami-Research and Background Materials-Handwritten notes (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Cubans in Miami-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Cubans in Miami-Correspondence-Incoming (Box 3, Folder 9)
- A Mind to Stay Here (1970)
  - Manuscript (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Galley Proofs (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Research and Background Materials-James Dabbs (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Research and Background Materials-John Lewis (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Research and Background Materials-Howard (Buck) Kester (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Research and Background Materials-Fannie Lou Hamer (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Research and Background Materials-Lucius Pitts and U. W. Clemon (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Research and Background Materials-Sarah Boyle (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Research and Background Materials-John Howard Griffin (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Research and Background Materials-Billie and DeDe Pierce (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Research and Background Materials-Charles Haynes (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Research and Background Materials-James Bevel (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence-Incoming (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Nashville Public School Desegregation (1970)
  - Federal Court Documents (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - School Board Meetings and Memoranda (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - CCIS (Concerned Citizens For Improved Schools)-Memos (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - CCIS-Correspondence-Outgoing (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - CCIS-Correspondence-Incoming (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - CCIS-Organization and Membership (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - CCIS-Activities and Events (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - CCIS-Published or Circulated Articles (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - CCIS-Published or Circulated Articles (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Nashville Public School Desegregation (1970-76)
  - Committee on School Zoning-Memos and Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Committee on School Zoning-Organization and Recommendations (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Other School Board Advisory Committees (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Research and Background Materials-School Statistics-1964-67 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Research and Background Materials-School Statistics-1967-69 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Research and Background Materials-School Statistics-1970 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Research and Background Materials-School Statistics-1970 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Research and Background Materials-School Statistics-1971 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Research and Background Materials-School Statistics-1971 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Research and Background Materials-School Statistics-1974-76 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Nashville Public School Desegregation (1971)
  - School Improvement Study (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Opinion Survey (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Research and Background Materials-Newspaper articles (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Research and Background Materials-Newspaper articles (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Media Coverage (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Community Involvement and Reaction (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Interviews for proposed Saturday Review article (Box 7, Folder 9)
- A Description of the Planning Process at Xavier University of New Orleans (1971)-Manuscript (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Jackson, Mississippi School Desegregation (1971)-Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Jackson, Mississippi School Desegregation -Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 8, Folder 3)
- The Black Public Colleges (Race Relations Information Center, 1971)-Manuscript (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Culebra, Puerto Rico and Ruben Berrios Martinez (1971)-Manuscript (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Culebra, Puerto Rico and Ruben Berrios Martinez-Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Culebra, Puerto Rico and Ruben Berrios Martinez-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Culebra, Puerto Rico and Ruben Berrios Martinez-Research and Background Materials- Handwritten Notes (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Culebra, Puerto Rico and Ruben Berrios Martinez-Correspondence-Outgoing (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Culebra, Puerto Rico and Ruben Berrios Martinez-Correspondence-Incoming (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Black Students and the University: A Conference Overview -(Southern Regional Education Board, 1971)-Manuscript (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Black Students and the University: A Conference Overview-Research and Background Materials-Handwritten Notes (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Black Students and the University: A Conference Overview-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Black Students and the University: A Conference Overview-Research and Background-Conference Materials, April 25-27, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Black Students and the University: A Conference Overview-Correspondence-Outgoing (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Black Students and the University: A Conference Overview-Correspondence-Incoming (Box 8, Folder 16)
- New Colleges for New Students (1972)
  - Manuscript/ Introduction (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript-Chapters on Malcolm-King Harlem College Extension (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript-Chapters on Nairobi College (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Manuscript-Chapters on Pima College (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Planning and Outlines (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Research and Background Materials-Malcolm-King Harlem College Extension (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Research and Background Materials-Nairobi College (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Research and Background Materials-Pima College (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence-Outgoing (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence-Incoming (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Private Education in Nashville (1972)-Manuscript (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Private Education in Nashville-Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Private Education in Nashville-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Private Education in Nashville-Correspondence-Incoming (Box 10, Folder 4)
- New South Mythology: A Festive Reunion of the Faithful (Race Relations Reporter, Mar. 6, 1972)-Manuscript (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 5)
- New South Mythology-Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Box 10, Folder 6)
- New South Mythology-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 10, Folder 7)
- New South Mythology-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Brown vs. the Board of Education, 18 Years Later (Race Relations Reporter, May 1972)-Manuscript (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Brown vs. the Board of Education-Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Paulo Freire Workshop, Frogmore S.C., January, 1972-Handwritten Notes for Manuscript (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Paulo Freire Workshop-Planning and Outlines (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Paulo Freire Workshop-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 10, Folder 13)
- Paulo Freire Workshop-Correspondence-Incoming (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Greenville, S.C. School Desegregation (1972)-Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Box 10, Folder 15)
- Greenville, S.C. School Desegregation-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 10, Folder 16)
- Greenville, S.C. School Desegregation-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 10, Folder 17)
- Report Card on Southern School Desegregation (Saturday Review, April 1, 1972)-Manuscript (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Report Card on Southern School Desegregation-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Report Card on Southern School Desegregation-Research and Background Materials-Research notes (Box 11, Folder 3)
- That New South (The Progressive, April, 1972)-Manuscript (Box 11, Folder 4)
- That New South-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Robert Burns Eleazer (1972)-Research and Background Materials-Interviews (2 copies) (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Robert Burns Eleazar-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Robert Burns Eleazar-Research and Background Materials-Eleazar’s Autobiography (Box 11, Folder 8)
- How to Eradicate an Indian Tribe (Race Relations Reporter, 1973)-Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Box 11, Folder 9)
- How to Eradicate an Indian Tribe- Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 11, Folder 10)
- How to Eradicate an Indian Tribe- Correspondence-Incoming (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Learning to Cope (1973)-Typed manuscript (Box 11, Folder 12)
- Learning to Cope -Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Box 11, Folder 13)
- Learning to Cope-Correspondence-Incoming (Box 11, Folder 14)
- Duke University (Change, 1973)-Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Box 11, Folder 15)
- Duke University-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 11, Folder 16)
- Duke University-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 11, Folder 17)
- Duke University-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 11, Folder 18)
- Duke University-Correspondence-Incoming (Box 11, Folder 19)
- The Americanization of Dixie (1973)
  - Manuscript (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Galley Proofs (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Galley Proofs (Box 12, Folder 4)
- The Americanization of Dixie
  - Planning and Outlines (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Agriculture) (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Research and Background Materials-Articles (Agriculture) (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Research and Background Materials- Articles (Contemporary South) (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Research and Background Materials-Research notes (Contemporary South) (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Land) (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Research and Background Materials-Articles (Land) (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Education) (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Research and Background Materials-Articles (Education) (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Industry) (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Research and Background Materials-Articles (Industry) (Box 13, Folder 11)
- The Americanization of Dixie
  - Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Politics) (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Research and Background Materials-Articles (Politics) (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Cities) (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Research and Background Materials-Articles (Cities) (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Culture) (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Research and Background Materials-Articles (Culture) (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence-Outgoing (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence-Incoming (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Publication Materials (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Reviews (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Promotional Materials (Box 14, Folder 11)
- Memphis School Desegregation (1973)
  - Manuscript (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Research and Background Materials-Activities of IMPACT (Involved Memphis Parents Assisting Children and Teachers) (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Research and Background Materials-Activities of NAACP Legal Defense Fund (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence-Incoming (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Reviews (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Southern Regional Council Textbook Conference, 1973-Typescript of draft of article (2 copies) (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Textbook Conference-Planning, Agenda, & Participants (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Textbook Conference-Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Textbook Conference-Research and Background Materials-Articles (General) (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Textbook Conference-Research and Background Materials-Articles (TN and NC) (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Textbook Conference-Research and Background Materials-Articles (FL) (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Textbook Conference- Research and Background Materials-Handwritten notes (Box 16, Folder 7)
- Textbook Conference -Correspondence-Outgoing (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Textbook Conference-Correspondence-Incoming (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Fisk University (1974)-Handwritten notes for a report (Box 16, Folder 10)
- Ending Discrimination in Higher Education (1974)-Manuscript (Box 16, Folder 11)
- Ending Discrimination in Higher Education-Planning and Outlines (Box 16, Folder 12)
- Ending Discrimination in Higher Education-Research and Background Materials-Statistical Data, State Plans for Increasing Black Presence In Higher Education (Box 16, Folder 13)
- John Popham (1974)-Manuscript (Box 16, Folder 14)
- John Popham-Research and Background Materials-Interview (Box 16, Folder 15)
- John Popham-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 16, Folder 16)
- Southern Regional Council Textbook Project-Florida (1974)-Memo concerning Direction of the project (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Southern Regional Council Textbook Project-Florida-Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Southern Regional Council Textbook Project-Florida-Research and Background Materials-Reports to State Legislative Committees (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Southern Regional Council Textbook Project-Florida-Research and Background Materials-State Laws (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Southern Regional Council Textbook Project-Florida-Research and Background Materials-Criteria for Textbook Selection (Box 17, Folder 5)
- Southern Regional Council Textbook Project-Florida-Research and Background Materials-State Textbook Selection Councils (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Southern Regional Council Textbook Project-Florida-Research and Background Materials-Catalog of Textbooks Adopted for NY (Box 17, Folder 7)
- Southern Regional Council Textbook Project-Florida-Research and Background Materials-Textbooks Submitted for 1974 Adoption (Box 17, Folder 8)
- Southern Regional Council Textbook Project-Florida-Research and Background Materials-Budget Requests for Textbooks (Box 17, Folder 9)
- Southern Regional Council Textbook Project-Florida-Research and Background Materials-State Forms for Requisition and Inventory of Textbooks (Box 17, Folder 10)
- Southern Regional Council Textbook Project-Florida-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 17, Folder 11)
- Southern Regional Council Textbook Project-Florida-Correspondence-Incoming (Box 17, Folder 12)
- The Great Hope Watermelon Caper (Southern Voices, March/April, 1974)-Manuscript (Box 17, Folder 13)
- The Great Hope Watermelon Caper-Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Box 17, Folder 14)
- Western Kentucky University (1974)-Manuscript (Box 17, Folder 15)
- Western Kentucky University-Interviews (Box 17, Folder 16)
- Western Kentucky University-Correspondence-Incoming (Box 17, Folder 17)
- Report of the Commission on the Future of the South (1974)
  - Manuscript (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Planning and Outlines-Committee Rosters and Agendas (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Planning and Outlines-Committee Reports (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Research and Background Materials-Report on Housing (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Research and Background Materials-Southern Growth Policies Board (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Reviews (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence-Outgoing (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence-Incoming (Box 18, Folder 10)
- REACH Project of the Fund for the Improvement of Higher Education (1974)-Manuscript (Concerns Distance Learning via Closed Circuit TV) (Box 19, Folder 1)
- REACH Project-Planning and Outlines (Box 19, Folder 2)
- REACH Project-Research and Background Materials-Interviews (Box 19, Folder 3)
- REACH Project-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 19, Folder 4)
- REACH Project-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 19, Folder 5)
- REACH Project-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 19, Folder 6)
- REACH Project-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 19, Folder 7)
- REACH Project-Research and Background Materials-Articles (Box 19, Folder 8)